Beth: Alongside the more common conditions
which co-occur with Autism, there are
other classic medical conditions such
as epilepsy, gastrointestinal and
feeding issues or sleep disorders.
Joe: Resolving sleep or gastrointestinal
problems may also offer behavioural
benefits, as the quantity and
quality of sleep can affect the
severity of repetitive behaviours.
Half of children with Autism have
trouble falling or staying asleep and
this could make their Autism worse.
Beth: Researchers recognise that sleep is
needed for brain development and improved
health, it improves mood, behaviour
and our mental state and therefore the
lack of it is likely to have impact.
Epilepsy can also be a problem.
Symptoms include shaking, having seizures,
and staring blankly into space are
closely linked to Autism characteristics.
Joe: Also genetic conditions, such as
fragile X syndrome and tuberous sclerosis
complex are closely linked to Autism.
One of the symptoms of Fragile X syndrome
is mild to severe intellectual disability
and individuals with the syndrome,
display a wide variety of Autism features.
Other neurological symptoms include
developmental delay and seizures.
Beth: It has been found that many children
with Tuberous sclerosis will be diagnosed
with Autism spectrum disorder and there
is a clear link with cognitive impairment.
Whichever condition an individual has,
alongside their Autism spectrum disorder,
the conditions often seem inter-related.
Joe: Some seem to be have a negative
impact such as sleep issues.
Some can mask their main disorder
such as ADHD, but they have to be
looked at individually alongside
each other to assess their impact
on each other and subsequently the
individuals health and well-being.